Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we continue our series
on ways to boost the production of
the important metabolic enzyme NAD+
by reviewing a supplement called NMN.
Both NR and NMN have been shown
to have beneficial effects in rodents,
though they haven’t
been tested side-by-side.
Both precursors raise blood
levels of NAD+ in people
but similarly haven’t been pitted
head-to-head against one another.
One potential advantage
of NMN over NR
is that it may be more
stable in the bloodstream.
In mouse blood at least, within an hour,
most NR is converted into NAM,
whereas NMN levels remain steady.
You could also argue that NMN is better
because it’s a direct precursor of NAD+,
whereas NR first has
to be converted to NMN;
so, we might as well just
take NMN in the first place.
Ironically, the exact opposite
argument can also be made
based on the inability of NMN to
pass through cell membranes.
Structurally, NMN is just NR with
a phosphate group attached to it.
The phosphate charge prevents NMN
from passing in and out of cells;
so, to get inside a cell, NMN first
has to be converted into NR.
Then, once inside, the NR can turn
back into NMN and make NAD+.
So, if NMN first has to be converted
into NR for cell entry, the argument goes,
maybe you might as well
just take NR to begin with,
because there’s no
NMN transporter.
Or is there?
An NMN transporter was recently
described (at least in mouse intestine);
so, maybe NMN is
able to skip the NR step
and pass directly into cells
to make NAD+ after all.
However, the evidence that such a NMN
transporter exists remains controversial.
NMN boasts a long list of
rodent healthspan benefits,
but, unlike NR, has yet to demonstrate
an extension of mammalian lifespan.
What about in people?
There have just been a few human
NMN studies published to date.
One small study of healthy
middle-aged men
found that various single doses
had no apparent effect
on any of the measured variables,
including retinal eye function,
sleep quality, heart rate,
blood pressure,
oxygenation,
or body temperature.
A 12-week study of daily NMN supplementation
in middle-aged men and women
similarly found no significant
effects on any outcome,
including lean mass,
muscle mass, body fat,
blood sugars, cholesterol,
or insulin sensitivity.
NMN did boost blood NAD+ levels,
though they peaked after the first month
and then trended down
for months two and three;
so, there may have been an
adaptive drop in NAD+ synthesis
as was suspected with NR.
Like NR, NMN also fails to
raise NAD+ in muscle tissue.
One study evocatively entitled,
“Nicotinamide Mononucleotide Supplementation
Enhances Aerobic Capacity in Amateur Runners,”
tested three different doses of
NMN versus placebo for six weeks
among young and middle-
aged recreational runners.
Aerobic capacity was increased at one
ventilatory threshold, but not the other.
No overall benefit for aerobic
capacity or peak power
or any of another ten measures of
cardiopulmonary function was found.
If you measure enough things,
statistical outliers,
both positive and negative ones,
can just pop up as flukes.
For example, the researchers
noted significant improvement
in the single-leg stance test,
but the NMN had no significant effect on
any of the other physical function tests.
And upon closer inspection,
the apparent single-leg balance benefit
was only found in the middle-dose group
compared to the high-dose group,
because the high-dose group ended up
doing slightly worse compared to baseline.
No significant effect was found for
any of the doses compared to placebo.
A similar issue can be found in a 12-week
study of NMN supplementation in older adults.
The NMN company-funded
authors concluded
that NMN “improved lower limb function
and reduced drowsiness in older adults.”
But it failed to significantly
affect 16 additional measures,
including other tests of lower
limb function and fatigue.
There are so few NMN studies that this
kind of shotgun approach is understandable,
casting the widest possible net
for effects to be further tested,
but on their own cannot be presented
as convincing proof of efficacy.
All of the above NMN studies
were on healthy individuals.
What about testing NMN on those who
are already metabolically compromised?
Overweight or obese postmenopausal
women with prediabetes
were randomized to NMN
or placebo for 10 weeks.
NMN didn’t seem to affect
body weight or composition,
liver fat, blood pressure,
or a dozen other metabolic variables,
but it did improve
muscle insulin sensitivity,
though not enough to affect insulin levels
or short- or long-term blood sugar control.
This may be because insulin sensitivity
in the liver and body fat remained unchanged.
NMN also appeared to have no
effect on mitochondrial function
or muscle strength,
fatigability, or recovery.
In terms of safety, NMN shills speak of it as
being naturally found in fruits and vegetables,
but even the most concentrated sources
(edamame, avocado, and broccoli)
have over a hundred times less per serving
than the typical NMN supplement dose.
The same could be said for NR in milk
(human and otherwise).
There are safety evaluations for NMN
on rats and dogs, but unlike NR,
supplemental doses of NMN have yet to
be shown as safe for human consumption.
There are rodent studies
showing that NMN
may have negative metabolic
consequences compared to placebo,
but the most serious concern
is nerve degeneration.
The accumulation of NMN
in nerve cells is toxic.
Since NR is converted into NMN,
this is a major concern for
NR supplementation as well.
The type of nerve damage,
axon degeneration,
is a major contributor to a variety
of neurodegenerative disorders.
Blocking an NMN-synthesizing enzyme
appeared to help damaged neurons in vitro,
protection that’s abolished
by adding NMN back,
and adding an enzyme that chews up
NMN was also found to be protective,
further supporting a theory of degenerative
effects of accumulating NMN.
However, clinical effects
remain theoretical,
as these adverse effects have only been
demonstrated in fish, mice, and petri dishes.
Of course, NMN supplements may not
even have NMN in the first place.
ChromaDex, which sells the rival
supplement Tru Niagen (a form of NR),
claims to have tested the 22 NMN brands
with the highest market share on Amazon
and found that most had
virtually no NMN at all.
Ironically, many of the apparently fake
NMN products displayed quote-unquote
“certificates of analysis” and carried
hundreds or thousands of positive reviews.
Evidently, only 3 out of 22 were found to contain
as much NMN as advertised on their label.
Of course, ChromaDex isn’t
above being shady itself;
it’s been accused of making
hyped false claims for Tru Niagen
by both the FDA and the
Better Business Bureau.
In short, NR has been demonstrated
to be relatively safe but not effective,
and neither safety nor efficacy
has been established for NMN.
What about all the other purported
NAD-boosting supplements?
Let’s find out.
Taking niacin,
also called nicotinic acid,
would be about 50 times
more efficient
than taking
the amino acid tryptophan
to boost NAD+,
because only about two percent
of tryptophan
is converted into niacin.
Also, tryptophan didn't work
to improve mitochondrial
or muscle function
in physically compromised
older adults,
even when combined
with niacin or nicotinamide.
And side effects
of taking tryptophan
include belching and gas,
blurred vision,
diarrhea, dizziness,
drowsiness, dry mouth,
headache, heartburn,
and potentially
a life-threatening condition
known as eosinophilia-myalgia
syndrome, or EMS.
There was an epidemic of EMS
tied to tryptophan supplements
from a single supplier
back in 1989
that led to their removal
from the market
for about 15 years.
Some sort of contaminant
was suspected,
but the cause
remains a mystery.
To this day,
tryptophan supplements
continue to be tainted
with impurities,
with at least one case
of EMS reported
decades after
the initial epidemic.
A case of EMS tied to
a bizarre weight loss diet
involving hundreds of cups
(~48 L) of cashews,
a rich source of tryptophan,
suggests the syndrome
can be caused
by excess tryptophan directly.
If anything,
tryptophan restriction
may be beneficial.
Nearly 50 years ago,
it was demonstrated
that restricting
dietary tryptophan
reduced cancer rates
and increased
the lifespans of rats
and, subsequently, mice.
Vegetarians and vegans
both appear to have
significantly lower intakes
of tryptophan,
but only in vegans
does this translate
to lower
tryptophan blood levels,
though presumably not
if they were to take
tryptophan supplements.
What about taking NAD+ directly?
This isn't practical
because of instability
and poor bioavailability.
NAD+ is vulnerable to heat,
pH, light, and oxygen,
requiring dark desiccant storage
at ideally 20 degrees (-29°C)
below freezing.
NAD+ can be given intravenously,
a practice started
in the 1950s
as an "underground" treatment
for alcoholism,
but when taken orally,
NAD may be broken down
in the alkaline environment
of the small intestine,
and NADH,
the so-called "reduced" form
of NAD+,
is broken down
in the acidic conditions
of the stomach.
(In organic chemistry,
the gain of a hydrogen atom
is said to quote-unquote
"reduce" the molecule,
so NADH
is the reduced form of NAD+).
Enteric forms of NAD+
could potentially survive
the digestive tract, but,
with the exception of neurons,
NAD can't cross
into mammalian cells.
This is why
NAD+ precursor supplements,
like NMN and NR,
were developed.
Also, there are evidently
(unpublished) data
showing that straight NAD+
can cause severe hyperglycemia
in mice.
Has it been tested in people?
NAD+ boosting supplements
have been found
to improve the learning
and memory of rodent models
of Alzheimer's disease
in the lab.
In 1995, case reports
of apparent benefit of NADH
for Alzheimer's disease
were published.
By the next year, an open-label
pilot study was published,
suggesting it had
a protective effect,
but without
a placebo control group,
the only conclusion
that could be drawn
was to study it further,
especially since
a similar study
with the same dose
over approximately
the same period
found no evidence
of any cognitive effects.
There have been
two randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
of NAD precursors
for Alzheimer's.
One found no benefit
for memory, attention,
or clinician ratings
of dementia severity,
but did maybe find
less of a drop
in one dementia rating scale
after six months
of 10 milligrams a day of NADH.
The other, a six-month study
of nicotinamide,
failed to find
any clinical effects.
What about trying
NMNH and NRH,
the reduced forms
of NMN and NR?
They both appear
to boost NAD+ higher
than their
non-reduced counterparts.
In vitro,
NMNH can raise NAD+ levels
up to 10 times higher than NMN,
and NRH (also known as
dihydronicotinamide riboside)
is up to about 50 times
more potent than NR.
There are concerns
about stability of NRH
outside the body,
since it's sensitive to oxygen
and moisture,
but within the body,
NRH may be more stable,
not rapidly devolving
into nicotinamide,
like NR does
(at least in mouse blood).
However, unlike NR,
NRH does not appear
to be able
to significantly increase levels
in mouse muscles.
NRH is said to have
a "spectacular potency"
for increasing NAD+ levels,
perhaps the most potent
precursor discovered to date.
This may not necessarily be
a good thing.
The extreme boost
afforded by NRH
had detrimental consequences
in human liver cells in vitro,
resulting from
an excessive accumulation
of free radicals.
In addition to oxidation,
NRH was also found
promote inflammation.
Pro-inflammatory effects
were noted for NRH
on human immune cells in vitro
(but not for NMN, NAM, or NR).
Because it appears that NMNH
is converted to NRH
to enter cells,
these potentially
deleterious effects
may be shared
by NMNH as well
(though this has yet
to be tested).
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.